Consumers' League of New York City Records 5307
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Consumers' League of New York City Records
1893-1962
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Consumers' League of New York City
5307
32.5 cubic feet
32.5 linear ft.
Minutes, reports, pamphlets, correspondence, publications.
The bulk of this collection covers the period from 1940 through the 1950's, although there are earlier documents scattered throughout. The organization's primary efforts appeared directed to developing protective legislation for migrant workers and their children in the state, although there is evidence of substantial activity on child labor, New York State disability insurance, equal pay, industrial homework, minimum wage, and women workers.
3338479
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 25, 2003
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 30, 2015
Biographical / Historical
The Consumer's League of New York City was formed in 1891 as a result of a report made in 1890 by Alice Woodbridge, secretary of the Working Women's Society, the forerunner of the Women's Trade Union League. This report enumerated the deplorable working conditions and long hours under which women engaged in the retail trade had to work. A small group of women proceeded to organize the league, whose first activity was to prepare a white list of shops paying minimum fair wages and having shorter hours and better sanitary conditions. In 1899, other leagues formed in Boston, Philadelphia, and Chicago united to form the National Consumer's League. Mr. John Graham Brooks was elected president and Florence Kelley, who had worked with Jane Addams at Hull House, Chicago, was made executive secretary.
Investigations were undertaken by the Consumer's League in many areas. The first concerned the conditions of manufacture and sale of women's and children's stitched cotton underwear, and was soon extended to other branches of the needle trades. Investigations were conducted into the conditions of unsanitary tenement homework and sweatshops, laundries, restaurants, textile mills, canneries, and candy factories. Reports of the Consumer's Leagues were usually pioneer revelations of undesirable working conditions and were accepted as authoritative by legislators and educational institutions.
Reports and agitations of the league were probably more influential in the field of legislation than in any other way and effected the passage, enforcement, and defense of laws having to do with safety, sanitation, night work, maximum hours, child labor, minimum wages, socIal security, and fair employment practices. Investigations, reports, and publicity were made the basis of pressure on legislatures and Congress, and in these campaigns the league has frequently had the cooperation of the American Association for Labor Legislation, the League for Industrial Democracy, the National Child Labor Association, the National Women Suffrage Association, and the League of Women Woters. It has also stimulated the creation of official bodies either for special investigation or for continuous administration, as in the case of the federal and state bureaus of women in industry and the Federal Children's Bureau.
Although not always in agreement wth trade unions, the league often cooperated with them in achieving ends jointly desired. It frequently obtained the active cooperation of employers in raising standards in instances where the ultimate interest of the employer coincides with that of the worker.
After World War II, the New York league called attention to the plight of migratory farm workers in the state. The league conducted extensive investigations of camp conditions, wages, and hours of migratory workers in 1945 and again in 1951.
Scope and Contents
The records document research and lobbying activities for federal and state legislation and various social action programs. They consist of routine business records, published and unpublished reports, correspondence, and research documents pertaining to equal pay, equal rights, minimum wage, child labor, women workers, migrant workers, and fair labor standards.
Organization records (1905-1955) consist of proceedings, resolutions, and reports of annual meetings (1930-1955); minutes of the Board of Directors (1937-1954); annual reports (1905-1916); and routine correspondence, press releases, programs, and speeches pertaining to the arrangements for the League's 50th anniversary (1949).
Research materials (1904-1955) consist of documents collected and produced by the League's staff and members to facilitate its legislative actions and research projects. Include memoranda; manuscript notes; bulletins; research documents; miscellaneous letters, and correspondence of various League officers and staff, including Florence Kelley, with political figures and other social action agencies concerning federal and state legislation and social action programs in occupational health and safety, labor relations, equal rights amendments (1925-1955), "candy white lists" boycotts (1929-1933), public education, equal pay, health insurance (1946), wages, hours and working conditions for women, children and migrant workers, migrant labor camps, wage and hour legislation, war labor standards, disability insurance, New York State household workers (1938), work at home (1934-1945), unemployment insurance (1933-1936), defense production, New York State Minimum Wage Boards, New York savings bank insurance (1938), and social security.
Also, reports, newsletters and pamphlets, chiefly of the League, pertaining to equal rights amendments, child labor, migrant workers and fair labor standards; and reports of the New York Minimum Wage Boards on the cleaning and dyeing, hotel, restaurant, retail trade and laundry industries (1933-1945).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Consumers' leagues. New York (State).; Consumers' League of New York City.
3338479
- Consumers League, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes miscellaneous publications, form letters and platform statement (1951-52)
- Consumers League, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Includes draft on project to improve conditions of migrant farm workers in New York State, letters to and from Henry B. Herman, The Society for Ethical Culture, form letters, newsletters, and minutes
- Consumers League, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes minutes of the Board of Directors, newsletter, statement of income and expenses (1952-53), Mary Heaton Vorse (Harper's Magazine) America's Submerged Class: the Migrants, and routine correspondence.
- Consumers League, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Includes minutes and routine correspondence
- Consumers League, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes letters to Assemblyman John L. Ostrander (Chairman, Labor & Industries Committee) and Senator Ernest I. Hatfield (Chairman, Labor and Industries Committee) soliciting support of the Metcalf -Waters Bill, and letters to Assemblyman William MacKenzie and Senator Austin Erwin urging support of Governor's budget for appropriations for an experimental summer school program for migratory farm worker's children
- Consumers League, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Includes statement to the Joint Legislative Committee On Industrial and Labor Conditions concerning safety regulations for children working on farms, report on the East Cutchogue Migrant Pilot Summer School, Newsletter, minutes, miscellaneous publications
- Consumers League, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Includes summary of recommendations adopted by Ad Hoc Conference on migrant labor (Dec.), 1956- 57 Budget, statement from Education for Migrant Children Committee, memos, minutes, newsletters and routine correspondence
- Consumers League, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes correspondence from the Liberal Party of New York State, supporting statement for an act to amend the labor law, a report on the State Education Dept. Pilot Project Summer School Education of Migrant Children (Sept. 1957), Fair Labor Standards Research Committee, record of members, supporters of Six-Point Program for Migrant Farm Labor in New York State, 1957-58 Budget, statement to Platform Committee of the N.Y.S. Democratic Committee, statement by Henry B. Herman before Joint Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions, 1958 Legislative Report, routine correspondence and newsletter
- Consumers League, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes Report on Farm Labor, letter to Senator Javits concerning Minimum Wage Act, list of Consumers League Board of Directors (1959-60), membership list of Westchester Ethical Society, Report on Migrant Labor, minutes, memos, routine correspondence, form letters, and letter to gov. n. Rockefeller concerning minimum wage
- Consumers League, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes copy of N.Y.S. Weekly Legislative Digest (Mar. 18), draft on Resolution to Memorialize Congress to Include Farm Workers under Fair Labor Standards Act, letter to President Elsenhower, Labor Secretary Mitchell, By-laws of the Consumers League of N. Y., Migratory Labor in New Jersey 1960, and statement In support of first class citizenship for voluntary hospital workers
- Consumers League, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Includes form letters, Consumers League of New Jersey Newsletter, pamphlets on the Newburgh Plan
- Consumers League, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes routine correspondence
- Consumers League (CL) Action - Federal - Migrant Labor: East Coast Migrant Conference, Washington, D.C., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  May, 1954
- CL Action - Federal - Fair Labor Standards Act, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- CL Action - Federal - Federal Commission on Migratory Labor: Bill to Establish, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- CL Action - Federal - Humphrey Sub-Committee Hearings on Migratory Farm Labor, 1952 (Box 1A, Folder 1)
- CL Action - Federal - Immigration and Naturalization Service, 1951-1952 (Box 1A, Folder 2)
- CL Action - Federal - Labor Department Budget, 1948 (Box 1A, Folder 3)
- CL Action - Federal - Migrant Labor - Appropriation, 1954 (Box 1A, Folder 4)
- CL Action - Federal - Children of Migrant Farm Workers, 1951 (Box 1A, Folder 5)
- CL Action - Federal - Price Control, 1947 (Box 1A, Folder 6)
- CL Action - Federal - Social Security - Proposed Program, 1948 (Box 1A, Folder 7)
  Fall 1948
- CL Action - Federal - Social Security Bill, 1948-1950 (Box 1A, Folder 8)
- CL Action - Federal - Wages - Proposed Program, 1948 (Box 1A, Folder 9)
- CL Action - Federal - 'Wetbacks' - Importation of, 1951 (Box 1A, Folder 10)
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance Citizens Committee (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Includes correspondence to and from the Disability Insurance Citizens Committee, letters to gov. Thomas E. Dewey concerning Disability Insurance Law, newsletters, memos, news release, form letters, and routine correspondence
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Forum, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  1/18/1951 Includes response to proposal to follow up the matter of the Disability Benefits Advisory Committee, correspondence with Mary Donlon (Workmen's Compensation Board) routine correspondence concerning the forum on the New York Disability Benefit Law, statement from N.Y. Times editor analyzing the Hughes-Brees Bill, letters to Gov. Thomas Dewey concerning Hatfield-Wadlin Bill, and resolution on disability insurance
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Forum, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  1/18/1951 Includes disability forum list, resolution on Disability Benefits Advisory Committee, letter from Herman E. Cooper stating reasons for defectiveness of the New York Disability Benefits Program and routine correspondence with members of the CL
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Forum Copies of speeches, releases and resolutions, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Testimony Before Democratic State Committee, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  12/12/1949 Includes statement by Professor Eveline M. Burns, President, Consumers League of New York for fair labor standards
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Proposed Pamphlet on operation of NY Disability Insurance Law (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Includes copy of proposed outline for pamphlet on the NY Disability Benefits Law and routine correspondence
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Gans Bills, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Contains letter from Eveline Burns to John F. Wadlin (Chairman, Committee on Labor and Industry) concerning Inadequacies of the present Disability Insurance Law, copy of Disability Compensation Law, Explanation of Disability Insurance Amendments proposed by the Consumers League of NY, and routine correspondence
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Testimony before Jt. Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  12/9/1947
- CL Action - Disability Insurance - Testimony before Jt. Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  12/8/49 Includes testimony of Professor Eveline M. Burns
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Testimony before Jt. Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  12/5/50 Includes testimony of Anne M. Montero, Executive Secretary of CL, an Act to Amend Workmen's Compensation Law, Explanation of Disability Insurance amendments proposed by the CL
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Testimony before Jt. Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  11/13/51 Includes statement by Professor Eveline M. Burns on the Disability Insurance Law
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Proposed Program, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Fall 1948 Includes proposed program for social security
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Spring 1949 Includes CL Points to Current State Programs in Arguing for Immediate Action on Disability Insurance, letters to the I.I. Times concerning the Disability Bill
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance - Recommendations of the CL Committee on Cash Disability Insurance, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  2/1/1949
- CL Action - NYS Disability Insurance, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Includes letter from CL to Senator Arthur H. Wicks concerning NY 1952 Legislative Program, platform statement NYS 1951-52 and legislative recommendations, and an Act In the Senate to Amend the Workmen's Compensation Law
- CL Action - NYS Equal Pay - Statement to Jt. Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  11/15/52 Includes statement of Consumers League of NY on Equal Pay
- CL Action - NYS - Government Employees - Proposed Programs, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Fall 1948 Includes proposed program for government employees
- CL Action - NYS Jt. Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Includes statement on behalf of the CL concerning the proposed State Minimum Wage Standards Act, Migrant Farm Labor in NYS, A Program for Action, and routine correspondence
- CL Action - US Migrant Labor, 1945-1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Includes work record of the Pike Labor Camp, the camp's history
- CL Action - NYS Migrant Labor - Legislative Action and Bill Promotion -, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Spring 1953 Includes routine correspondence, newspaper articles on the abuses in migrant labor camps, newspaper articles on the Peterson Bill, the Peterson Bill, the bill for the licensing of farm labor contractors introduced by Assemblyman Alonzo L. Waters
- CL Action - NYS Migrant Labor - Bill Preparation, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Includes proposed bluprint for a US Migrant Labor Law, letter from Stephen W. Blodgett to Beekman H. Pool (State Charities Aid Assn.) concerning problems with migrant farm labor, newspaper articles on migrant laborers, letter to Minna F. Kassner (Chairman, Migrant Labor Committee) from Frederick J. Moffitt (NYS Education Dept.) concerning migrant laborers children, letter to gov. Dewey concerning completed study of migrant labor in NYS, proposed blueprint for a NYS Migrant Labor Law, proposed program for promotion, distribution and follow-up of Migrant Labor Study, 1952, form letters and routine correspondence
- CL Action - NYS Migrant Labor - Bulletins (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Includes bulletins and memos
- CL Action - NYS Migrant Labor - Child Labor Law Enforcement, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Includes routine correspondence, letter to Edward Corsi (NYS Dept of Labor Industrial Commissioner) concerning child labor
- CL Action - NYS Migrant Labor - Children, Education of (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Includes routine correspondence, correspondence with the National Child Labor Committee, 1951-53
- CL Action - NYS Migrant Labor - Conference, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Jan. 1960 Includes letter sent to Assemblyman Waters explaining why migrant labor using areas needs investigation, bulletin on state legislation, Action Conference on Migrant Farm Labor Program, form letters, memos, summary of proposed bills
- CL Action - NYS Migrant Labor - Health Dept. Budget, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Includes statement on the proposed budget for the Dept. of Labor, routine correspondence, statement presented to the fiscal and tax committees of NYS Legislature, statement on health dept. budget, labor dept. statement, statement on migrant labor camps
- CL Action - NYS Migrant Labor - Licensing of crew-leaders, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- CL Action - Minimum Wage, 1945-1950 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Includes announcement of conference on wage policy
- CL Action - Night Work for Women, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Includes outline for study of 'Night Work for Women' and news release
- CL Action - NYS - Platform Statement, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Includes platform statement on wages and hours, statement on disability Insurance, minutes, memos, form letters, routine correspondence, a proposed act In relation to hours of labor for children, and Draft of 1951-52 Program for Minimum Wage
- CL Action - NYS - Policy Statements, 1954-1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Includes letter of Congressman E.C. Gathings discussing CL position on certain bills involving Mexican Farm Labor Importation Program, letter to gov. n. A. Rockefeller discussing the Javits bill which would require crew leaders of migrant labor camps to register with State, statement of CL on proposed standards regulating interstate recruitment of agricultural workers, statement submitted by CL to Platform Committee of US Republican Committee, statement submitted to Platform Committee of NYS Democratic Committee, statement in support of HR 11793 improvement of migrant labor conditions, statement on migratory labor legislation, letter to gov. Harriman stating the need for a single state agency to control migrant labor, and a newsletter
- CL Action - NYS - Program - Legislation, 1946-1948 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Includes CL announcement on the progress of the minimum wage order, and routine correspondence
- CL Action - NYS - Project, Migrant Labor - CL Bill, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Includes Migrant Labor Legislation Bulletin, an Act to Establish a Division of Migrant Farm Labor Within the Department of Labor, and correspondence discussing the act
- CL Action - NYS Program (Proposed), 1948 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Fall 1948 Includes copy of the tentative program 1948-49, proposed program for government employees, proposed programs for social security, wages, and welfare standards
- CL Action - NYS - Unemployment Insurance - Testimony before Democratic State Committee, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  12/12/49 Includes statement on disability Insurance and legislative programs
- CL Action - NYS - Unemployment Insurances, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Includes statement on the Hughes-Brees Bill (disability insurance), summary of minutes from a conference group on employment and vocational guidance steering committee, routine correspondence, the Hughes-Brees Act, and newsletter
- CL Action - NYS - Unemployment Insurance, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Includes platform statement and legislative recommendations and an act to amend the labor law in relation to providing coverage of one or more employees for unemployment insurance
- CL Action - NYS - Unemployment Insurance - Testimony before Jt. Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  11/15/51 Includes statement on unemployment insurance
- CL Action - NYS - Wages and Hours, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Includes comments re legislation proposed by Women's Trade Union League - Blank Bill
- CL Action - NYS - Wages and Hours - Special Minimum Wage Bulletins, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Includes leaflet 'The High Cost of Low Wages'
- CL Action - NYS - Wages - Proposed Program, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Fall 1948 Includes proposed programs for wages and welfare standards
- CL Action - NYS - Wages and Hours - Legislative Action, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Includes correspondence re Minimum Wage Bill
- CL Action - NYS - Wages and Hours - Legislative Action, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Includes correspondence re Metcalf Bill to amend Education Law in relation to newspaper carrier boys. Memos and correspondence re Minimum Wage Bill (Halpern-Preller), C.L. platform statement on wages and hours
- CL Action - NYS - Wages and Hours - Legislative Action, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Includes correspondence re Minimum Wage Bill, news-clippings, newsletters, correspondence re Hatfield-Wadlin Bill - child labor, special bulletin, minimum wage - laundry industry
- CL Action - NYS - Wages and Hours - Testimony before Democratic State Committee, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  12/12/49 Statement by E.M. Burns, President re disability insurance, unemployment insurance, wage and hour legislation, migrant workers
- CL Action - NYS - Wages and Hours - Testimony Before Jt. Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  11/13/51 Includes news release, statement of F. Wunderlich re women and children In industry, draft of platform statement on wages and hours
- CL Action - NYS - Wages and Hours - Action re Proposed 'State Minimum Wage Standards Act', 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Includes critical summary and statement re state Minimum Wage Standards Act, correspondence and proposed bill from Lazare Teper, ILGWU on state-wide minimum wage and routine correspondence
- CL Action - NYS - Wages and Hours - CL (Halpern-Preller) Minimum Wage Bill, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Includes bill (draft and printed forms)
- CL Action - NYS - Wages and Hours - Summary of Halpern-Preller Minimum Wage Bill, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- CL Action - NYS - Welfare Standards Proposed Program, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Includes proposed program, on welfare standards
- CL Action - NYS - Workmen's Compensation, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  Includes form letter sent to legislators re bills -fair labor standards, platform statement and Noonan and McCullough Bills
- CL Action - NYS - Workmen's Compensation - Proposed Program, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  Fall 1948 Includes program on social security
- CL Administrative Budget, 1948-1959 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  Includes budget and statements for fiscal years 1948 - 1959, comparative statement for 1950-51 and 1951-52, routine correspondence, statement on Migrant Labor Project (1952),
- CL Administrative - Miscellaneous Correspondences, 1948-1955 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  Includes sympathy letters to Mrs. Thacher Winslow and Mrs. F.F. Unhey; correspondence with Mary Heaton Vorse re migrant labor, inquiries concerning activities of CL from various correspondents, Association of American Indian Affairs, Inc. correspondence and newsletter